My name is Belle Decker. I escaped the
fundamentalist Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints. I was trapped there
for eight years. This is how crime
works.
Warren Jeffs being the prophet of the
FLDS, he had full control. In the public
eye, he was one person. In reality, he
was a criminal. If Warren Jeff told
somebody to do something, even if it was
wrong, they can't really say no. I tried
like 10 times to escape before I
succeeded.
I was born and raised in the FLDS faith.
I married Warren Jess at 18 years old.
Arranged marriages were established
because they had polygamy in the church
and they said arranged marriages is the
way it works because like if you go
through the prophet that's the only way
to be pure. I believed everything I was
told by my parents. I believed
everything I was told by Warren Jess.
Even Warren Jess became the prophet in
September of 2002. He was also the
closest one to God on earth supposedly.
That's why they call him the prophet.
When I was little, I wasn't really asked
what I want to be when I grow up. It was
always like, "You're going to be a
mother in Zion." Stuff like that. Like
it was just mapped out, you know, this
is how it's going to be. Warren and Jess
called my father. He told him I was
ready to get married. And my father was
told to take me on a drive. He didn't
know who I was going to marry for sure
at that time. It could have been any guy
in the church. We get up there and
Warren and Jeff's asked me, "Who do you
believe God wants you to marry?" I
didn't dare lie to him. I also didn't
dare say no to him in the end when he
confirmed that it was him because like I
felt like I was groomed. I also felt
like I don't feel like um I'm in a
position to really have a say, but I
also didn't know what I was going into.
It felt like standing on the edge of a
cliff. Now when I look back on it and
being told which way do you want to jump
off, you know, there was really no way
to to have an easy path. The FLDS women
did not really have a say in their
marriages. They could refuse, but like
they were strongly encouraged to say yes
cuz like the punishments, you know,
could be pretty steep. I had a sister
who went into his family 5 years before.
I was afraid like I I I saw how they
treated her. She wasn't really high
status in his family really. To reach
into his family from where I stood was
supposed to be a huge privilege for me.
I did not love Jeff's like I was more in
the marriage for God. Every marriage was
separate at the time when I was growing
up. Usually the first wife was the only
legal one
cuz that was the only one that could be
legal. They had different rooms and they
didn't usually combine all that until
Warren Jeff's went to Texas. In Warren
Jeff's house in Texas, they had bunk
beds in some of the bigger rooms. He had
a favorite wife and he was basically a
monogamist. Um he uh said God would
decide if ever you were worthy to be
with him. He did not have a rotation
cycle. So there was a chance you would
never see him. But but for me, I didn't
really care about that cuz I wasn't
really attracted to him. When he went to
Texas, had a guard tower and a gate
around it. He started to introduce like
what he was doing as group sessions.
>> What do you mean by group sessions? You
don't have to go into detail. Just
>> Yeah. Well, he was having orgies. So,
yeah, he was bringing underage brides in
the room with like adult wives. So, like
it was a very bad situation. You know, I
didn't know at the time I married him.
He wanted to make me an accomplice. He
knew that part of the story is very hard
for me to like talk about.
The Book of Mormon is one of the main
teachings that define the FLDS. The FLDS
church is a branch off of the mainstream
Latter-day Saints church. The F stands
for fundamentalist. In the LDS faith,
they interpret the Book of Mormon to
have eternal families and they baptize
people in the temples for eternity and
stuff. In the FLDS, they believe that
everything belongs to God. So, they've
interpreted the scriptures quite a bit
different over the years. And they say
that the children belong to the prophet,
you know, to to the to God through the
prophet. So, they actually have
paperwork that you sign your children
over to the church of the FLDS, which is
not legal paperwork, but they don't all
know that. In the early 1900s, the LDS
and the FLDS split because of polygamy.
If you are just in a monogous marriage,
you'll never see God again. You have to
have three wives to make it into heaven.
LDS do not like LDS. They think they're
following the wrong prophet. So, they
call them apostates. LDS don't really
like FLDS either for the same reason.
Before Warren Jeff became the leader,
there was 10,000 followers. I believe um
that he has at least 5,000 today. Being
the profit of the FLDS, um he had full
control. He had the titles of their
houses in this legal trust called the
UE. So the UE is um United Effort Plan.
It's like the land in Colorado City in
Hildell. He had control of who lived in
the houses because he had the titles. he
could decide if he wanted to move
somebody and he had a moving crew that
would just show up at your house and say
you're moving today. He had control of,
you know, the food, you know, how much,
you know, people were able to like cuz
he didn't let the ladies especially
leave his ladies leave their houses. So
he would have people bring food to us.
So like what they brought was what he
wanted them to bring, you know?
It's like a pyramid in the FLDS. They
have the prophet, they have the bishops,
they have the fathers, the mothers,
children at the bottom. And in war and
just family, he had a pyramid also. And
it had to do with heritage a lot
according to obedience. When I entered
the family, I was number 65. I think he
only had 49 children altogether. Family
to family, it did vary quite a bit. Um,
in Warren and Jess's family, we lived
off donations, so we didn't really work
for money. It was a hard balance when
you forget like how how hard it is to
earn money. And when you have 79 wives,
you can only imagine, you know, like for
a time there was Wendell Nelson and Mel
Jessup who were the first presidency.
And then the bishops over different
areas were like his brother Isaac, his
brother Lyall. He had different people
over different areas that were bishops,
but it varied quite a bit because he
struggled with like trusting and feeling
like people were going to overpower him
someday and become the prophet later.
So, he would excommunicate bishops and
stuff for for temporary and sometimes
for um out of the church like he would
just like accuse them of crimes and
rotate them quite often. Um there were
other reasons also why people were
rotated but that was the main reason is
because of his his insecurities. Each
person had to prove their loyalty to get
into like the higher positions. So if
they were first presidency they were
like pretty loyal to Warren Jeffs and
had higher standards. Being a wife did
not give you any power and control
except for like with the community
members like if you're with like in my
family they would respect me more while
I was part of the FLDS because I was
married to Warren Jess because like I
knew more I had I went straight to the
source to find out information. Also
like another thing was that if you're
married to the prophet that's the
highest a woman can go in the church. I
did not get along with everyone there.
That was basically impossible with 79
wives. But um I did have some friends.
People fight especially in polygamy like
the wives they have the jealousy issue
and like it's very hard to keep sweet no
matter what you know like it's very very
hard when like um it's not fair you know
and there's not never going to be fair.
People do fight they just don't fight
like people would without the
psychological component. they reach
their breaking point and you know they
have breakdowns, they end up in
hospitals, you know, they end up the
same things, but like there's more
pressure. So, it's going to happen more
often. But then they're also denied
medical resources a lot in these cults.
So,
it's very hard.
Doctrine and covenants is the one
section 132 talks about like polygamy.
Um, that was the one that they use in
the FLDS. The main duties of the wives
were like cooking, cleaning, gardening,
sewing, teaching, school, interacting
with the children, like in between
school. When I first married Warren
Jess, he put me on like every chore.
Like every hour I'd be on like gardening
for an hour, sewing for an hour. Like I
was running from job to job and I was so
exhausted by the end of the day. I don't
really know why he did that. All the
rules were strictly enforced except for
like more mild ones. you had more
layway. Being late was like one of those
milder ones like to the kitchen, to your
responsibilities, but if you you were
late because you slept in, you know,
it's going to have it's going to be one
of those ones that stack over time. So,
at first it won't be that big of a deal,
but over like 10 years, you're going to
have more offenses and there's a chance
that the punishments will become greater
by the end of the 10 years. Punishments
could be psychological as well as
physical punishments. Psychological
means like you can't grow beyond your
state like into heaven. Um you will
never see God again. If you are never
highly promoted in the church, you're
going to like get deprived of like
physical blessings too. Like your house
might be more needy and then you can
move out of it when you fix it up and
never have a good house. So physical
punishments happen that way too.
Challenging the prophet was definite
excommunication from the church, lose
your family. It doesn't mean like, you
know, execute them, you know, like death
necessarily. It could lead to that, but
they would never say like if you did die
in the church, they usually put it in
the name of an accident. Members were
definitely expected to tattle. If they
saw anything, saw somebody out of line,
something bothered them, they were
encouraged to talk to war and just and
tell them about it. The people inside do
realize they are being controlled. But
they also are taught that there is they
have a choice. They can say no at any
time, but they don't know how it is to
say no without pressure. It's not really
agency. It's not really freedom. At 8
years old, when you're baptized,
from that point on, God stops atoning
for you. It's all up to obedience. If
you disobeyed in the FLDS, then um you
would never make it to the highest
degree of glory in the celestial
kingdom, which meant you would never see
God again. You had to make it to the
very top. One of their doctrines is like
you cannot have relationships with
pregnant women. And so War and Jeff
would take men's wives away saying like,
"You disobeyed the doctrine. You
disobeyed God and go and have
relationships with the same lady, you
know, marry her, have relationships with
her while she's pregnant." But he
didn't. He was the exception because
he's the prophet.
The LDS were not encouraged to interact
the outside world. They had to like go
to the stores at times and stuff, but
usually it was the men, you know, in War
and Jess family. When I was a younger
child, I did get to go to the stores in
Sandy with my mother and father, but
like we were encouraged to not interact.
So, a smile or just a compliment about
your hair or something meant a lot to me
at that time. Um because when I got in
crisis later in life, I felt like, you
know, those are the people that care,
the people on the outside. Even though I
was told my whole life they didn't care,
but those compliments and those smiles
showed me a different story than what I
was being told. He had a lot of control
over which books were recommended to
read, which books weren't, you know, and
over the years that's got stricter and
stricter. We had to get rid of the
televisions when I was like 9 years old.
And then internet was we couldn't have
internet basically around the time that
Warren Jess was caught. I think that was
a lot to protect the true stories
from getting to the people. Um, we did
have telephones. They would just like go
in and try to delete the internet
option. Um, we also had radio in the
cars, but like we weren't supposed to
turn it on, you know? Like they did have
some of the basic like computers and
stuff, but like they tried not to get on
the internet.
I lived in about 23 houses during the
time frame that I was in Warren as
family. The main locations at the time
was South Dakota, Colorado City, and
Texas. I did live in Texas the most
because it was where I was supposed to
be according to him. Houses in hiding
were mainly set up for people that were
struggling in the holy lands. So like
the compounds. So South Dakota, Colorado
City, Texas, they were places that if
you for the most obedient people, the
houses in hiding were like in between
like Hilldale and Colorado City and the
Holy Lands. And the main reason I think
the purpose was so they wouldn't mix
with the people in Hillell and Colorado
City, but they couldn't stay in Texas
because they were struggling. They
didn't want to mixing cuz then all the
information that was happening in Texas
and and those would get more out when
you started to struggle when he saw the
first signs of like questioning or
anything, he would move you to another
location. And most of the time they were
told to just pray and work to be able to
be sent back to the holy lands. For most
of the people their experience in these
houses I believe was like cooking and
you know sewing and just praying. But
like for me when I got there it was a
different experience cuz I just read and
became openly rebellious for 2 years.
Usually there was like seven women in a
house and then the caretaker and his
family. They weren't allowed to leave
the house because they wore the dresses
and people could identify them. And also
they could escape, you know, like if
they're struggling, he's not going to
want them going out and about in the
stores and all that kind of stuff. If
it's a caretaker over a woman, it was a
man. If it's a caretaker over children,
it's usually a lady. The man would have
his own family there and they would
guard us. Like we couldn't go outside.
We couldn't, you know, they had cameras
on us and there was really no exit
route. the more you struggled, the more
ch times you tried to escape and didn't
successfully escape, um the higher
security tight ends on you. Even a
child, like if a child tries to escape
and then has to go back legally,
they're probably going to have a harder
experience when they get back. I ended
up in the houses in hiding because I
requested to go there. I wrote to War
and Jeff right after one of those secret
group sessions. I only went into one of
those. Like it was basically um the
introduction to the whole situation and
I wrote to him and I told him I don't
really want to, you know, I just need
more time. I didn't confront him on his
ideas, but I just told him I needed more
time and he bought into my story and let
me go to a house in hiding to prepare
further. And I became openly rebellious
and did not go back until he was caught
by the law.
Children are raised in the FLDS to be
obedient. They they believe that by the
time they're 3 years old, they should
know what obedience is. They're taught
like, you know, what would father like?
What would father do in this situation?
What would the prophet do in this
situation? It's all about like the
pyramid, like the girls, you're going to
be a mother in Zion. There was so many
different trainings. like he had one on
almost every topic of life. What to eat,
you know, like when to eat, if you can
have naps during the day, like when to
go to bed for the women and when to go
to bed for the men. When I was a child,
we had at least 4 hours a day of like
sermons. And we had it in the morning
when we woke up with our father for an
hour. We had it at school when we first
got there for an hour with Warren and
Jess. We had it after lunch, history
training for an hour. and then at night
before we went to bed and then Sundays
of course were more education was mostly
homeschool for people in Salt Lake area
um the FLDS school but in I believe in
like Colorado City and Hilda there are a
lot of like the other children around
even my age that went to public school
for a time the schools were always
controlled by the church to some level
all the book work they had all that was
printed off like old books that they had
changed the wording and stuff to make it
more churchy. It was all controlled by
the church in the name of God.
Psychological
um warfare. Like I think that was the
main thing he used to keep people
obedient. Also like brainwashing from
birth. By the time they're 18 years old,
they have really strong, you know, brain
cells for like the FLDS lifestyle.
Children did not learn about the outside
world very well, especially if they
weren't raised around it. Lost Boys is a
media term, but it kind of signifies
something that is realistic. It's a
patriarchal society. So the the rules
were made stricter for the boys and also
I think a lot of that is because of
competition. They don't have enough
girls to go around. Not everybody can
have 79 wives, you know, like that's
just crazy. So they would kick out the
boys at young ages for for
non-compliance. By the time they were 8
years old, they could be kicked out. And
there were 8-year-olds that were kicked
out. But more often, I think it was more
like 12 and a little bit more teenage
ages. They were seen as a threat because
of marriage because of the polygamy. If
they're young and, you know, able-bodied
and stuff that they might be wanted more
than the 50-year-olds, you know, the
60-year-old, they're cut off from the
family. They get cut out of the
pictures. It's pretty traumatic. So,
it's a miracle. I even have any pictures
of me when I was younger cuz like I
don't have very many but like I had a
few secretly sent to me but like most of
the time they they burn all that you
know like it's they don't have record of
it.
>> What usually happens to them after
they're kicked out.
>> So in those days it was way harder for
them cuz there was no organizations
hardly. They would go to a local place
in St. storage that had mattresses and
they would open up the back door and all
the boys would sleep on their beds
during the night like their um packaged
beds, you know, that are displays and
they would all jump on those displays in
the nighttime and then they would close
up the shop and then the next morning
they'd let them out. And when the
activists got more wellknown and got
more established, the parents would try
to bring them straight up to the
organizations.
Mor and Jeff required of his followers
that they donate $1,000 per month per
18-year-old male in the household. So,
it came from the followers and it was
even at at the expense of their credit.
A lot of people when they leave the FLDS
either have no credit like what I had
cuz I was his wife. if I didn't work for
money. Women were not and are not to
this day allowed to work. I think it's
to keep them isolated and keep them
without resources. I think that was a
bad thing because like some of the wives
had lived off donations for so long.
They had no hesitation to ask for money.
And for the community members, it was a
lot to donate that much money. Like they
would go in and say, "Can I get LASIC
today?" And can I get like all white
feeling caps? You know, all these
different things. It was very strict.
The thousands a month was very strict
like it mattered to them that you
donated that. They had some FLDS
businesses also like machine shops. So
they just worked like a regular job and
would try any way they could to get the
money. That was the priority. More and
Jeff spent it lavishly like he spent the
money on like himself pretty much and he
even denied his family medical care and
stuff so he could have more money. When
they caught him, they had evidence of
like all these pictures of like he was
going to strip clubs. He was getting
tons of vehicles and rotating them so
that he didn't get caught by the law. He
was trying to like trade out his
vehicles quite often. He was very like
selfish like he he had tons of money and
he was just touring the world with it
basically. Nowadays he hides his assets
in his members names. He drained the
people of everything and just left it
sitting. He was a sociopath. He like
taking away hope and taking away you
know things slowly. The financial system
was part of it to attain his goal which
was to take away their hope
antagonizingly and slowly and painfully
make him isolated, make him lonely, you
know, like he wasn't really he just
wasn't a good guy. You know, he could
have done so many good things with him,
but he didn't want to. You would find
these people out in the world like
mainly in the construction field where
the boys are the 8-year-olds are driving
tractors like and they're not getting
paid. It's called labor trafficking, but
like they bid the jobs really low so
that because they're not paying labor
and they're able to get more jobs
because of that, you know, they're out
bidding everyone else. like you can come
across them like the women generally
aren't out and about so it's harder to
find them because they dress with the
prairie dresses in the FLDS and if they
did come to the stores you would see
them but um it's just more rare people
outside of the community they don't
always know they just know they got a
good bid you know for their project
until like later after they're on the
job some people don't care they think
they're good workers they do a good job
you know these polygamy Many families
don't have marriages cuz it's not legal
in America to be like married to the
same guy. So on their paperwork it looks
like they're single and so they get more
food stamps, they get more all this
stuff, government help. This guy was
saying that he that one sister wife will
claim the other sister wife's kids and
get like daycare support in home child
care. They actually get paid to watch
their own kids cuz they're claiming the
other sister wife's kids and this one's
claiming this sister wife's kids. So
then they get paid to watch their own
kids.
The main compound was was Texas yearning
for Zion Wrench when I was married to
him. There were like selected people who
went to Texas and that's how he started
to break up families and children even
leaving without their parents because he
was calling them forward. God called
them supposedly to this holy land. And
if War and Jeff told somebody to do
something, even if it was wrong, they
can't really say no. Like they would
they could get kicked out of the church
at that point and lose their family and
their kids and you know, everybody. He
sent me to a house and hide in Vegas. in
Vegas. I didn't really choose that. And
eventually I got to where I wrote him a
letter and I told him like he told us
never to talk about the orgy sessions,
but I wrote him a letter about like I
don't want to consummate our marriage in
front of everyone. And I never had up
until this point, which was a year
after. I told him I wasn't going to pray
until I wanted to. So I to ensure that I
didn't like go back to Texas before I
wanted to. I told him like I was going
to read though. I told him, "I'm not
going to pray, but I'm going to read."
That was mainly to stop the punishments
from like stacking and like happening to
me over and over. I never consumate the
marriage. So, like for me, I um I went
to these houses in hiding, became openly
rebellious, and he got caught by the law
before I went back to Texas. In mid to
late 2000s, the investigations began on
Warren Jeffs. He was on the 10 most
wanted list in America for a while
before he was caught. He he ran from the
law right when he became the prophet.
Elisa Wall's case is the one in Utah.
Her case was about like underage
marriage that he had performed before he
became the leader. The Utah case fell
through on a technicality for a short
time and he would have been released had
not they had gone into Texas compound
and found the records and put him in a
Texas prison. In 2008, Texas authorities
raided the yearning for Zion Ranch and
hundreds of children were temporarily
removed. And that's where like that
story about like you know where I wrote
that letter and flagged the authorities
in Warren Jeff's version. It helped them
find the evidence they needed to go into
Texas. His brother Seth Jeffs was caught
transporting his letters and put on
trial for aiding in abetting a fugitive.
When that letter got caught by the law
and flagged the authorities to go into
Texas, he was he was never going to
forgive me. When Warren Jess called me,
I knew he was angry to a point that I
had never seen him angry at me. He
talked to me about did you write a
letter? And I I confessed, you know, I
told him, "Yeah, cuz he already knew
like he he figured out, you know, cuz
they had a trial and stuff and so he
already knew they had that letter." I
didn't know exactly what it meant. I
didn't realize I had flagged
authorities, you know, on his case. He
didn't explain that to me. I was in
survival mode from basically the time
that letter was caught.
Warren just ran from the law. He
required more money of his people. He
also didn't want to be in Hildell or
Short Creek very much cuz the law
enforcement was watching that area more
than the other newer ones and they
didn't know where he was. When the Texas
raid happened, I was in South Dakota and
then they they were telling me the raid
was my fault. more unjust capture was my
fault. They transported us off of the
compound because they were afraid of the
raid going into Colorado City and South
Dakota. Also, the Texas location played
a big role because that's where they got
the evidence that put him in prison.
That was like the center stake. that was
where Warren and Jess wanted to be most
of the time before um they went in and
they call it an attempted rescue or a
raid but like the law officials went in
and found the records and prosecuted
Warren Jeffs and put him in prison.
There's been children come forward that
were molested by him. As mothers
realizing all this though is no, we had
not enough power to save them from that
because he was the prophet and you know
he had done so much stuff already. I had
no way of protecting those children.
When I talk about the children, I talk
about like the underage brides, also the
younger kids. He said one time that one
of the boys was going after him that was
accusing him of molesting him in uh the
school back in the day when he was the
principal. He would give out like
excuses and say like, you know, they
fabricated the evidence is another way
of like saying like it's not real. He
had so much at his fingertips to
gaslight people like convince them that
their true memories are not real. They
had arranged marriages first, then they
established underage bride. So like they
were commanded to have these wives and
have children with them. So it's just so
extreme. That's what makes me believe it
is a cult. I was so devastated. Like for
me it was like it was still like really
heavy and really sad cuz like you know
what happened to the children? Nobody
was standing up for them. they're all
deciding to just go along with it. I
would say probably the most
misunderstood thing in my experience is
that anybody who was over age of 18 is
not necessarily an accomplice. In 2011,
Warren Jess was convicted for sexual
assault and sentenced to life in 20
years.
The drugs came when I was 23 years old.
He started sending nurses and stuff to
to give me the medicine that the doctors
prescribed that I didn't even see the
doctor for. You know, it was very very
scary cuz I didn't know if I was even
going to wake up. I didn't know what
they were giving me. They told me it was
for sleep. It was really for mood
stabilizer and sleep. But like it was
cerical. They had cult doctors. So they
had doctors that were sent to college to
become doctors that were born and raised
in the FLDS. So they had like degrees
and stuff so they could get medication
for people. Warren Jeffs was never went
to college, but he I believe demanded
control over like his family's
medications through the doctors telling
the doctors if he didn't if he wasn't
able to prescribe medicine for his
family, then he would take away the
doctor's family. I didn't have internet.
I couldn't check up symptoms when I'm
asking for safety and they want to give
me medicine for sleep. I'm like, how am
I going to sleep even if I have medicine
if I'm not safe? So that was a big
wakeup call for me. I didn't really feel
like they were following this the
protocol they would follow with most of
their patients. To this day, I still had
repercussions from like my tongue is
like, you know, damaged from the
medications they gave me. I've been told
now that my uh caretaker who's left the
church now, he said that Warren Jeffs
had me come cold turkey off all of those
drugs two weeks before my escape. I knew
I came cold turkey off, but I thought it
was after they escaped cuz I didn't have
resources. War and Jeff knew that, but
he was willing to do that to try to
collect the evidence, I believe, to put
a guardian over me. But God had other
plans. I believe the doctor who had
control, most control over my health,
lost his family a month after my escape.
After I escaped, my father lost his
family a week later. My brother lost,
who was my caretaker at the time, lost
his family a month later. When a person
in the FLDS loses their family, there's
times when War and Jess will reassign
the family to another man or another
person in the FLDS, it's more qualified
to take care of them. But um when they
lose their family, sometimes it's just a
repentance mission. So like there's a
temporary time frame when they're not
allowed to see their family and then
they maybe can someday come back and see
them. My father was told he can never
come back to the church. My mother has
not been reassigned to this day that I
know of. But um my father, he's never
been able to be with her since you know
that you even hardly see her for years
now.
I think he was in prison before I
escaped. I tried like 10 times to escape
before I succeeded. Um 10 major times. I
had little little things but like every
time I got a hold of a phone book or you
know try to figure out where to go they
would see me you know so it was very
hard to escape and I believe when I did
escape it wasn't planned very well. I do
have a documentary on HBO Max and
Discovery Plus called Prisoner of the
Prophet and it goes into like one of the
first attempts that I went off. The
police actually had me and everything,
but they wanted to put me in a shelter
next to the compound, you know, like it
was too close to the compound for
comfort for me. I felt like it wasn't
like going to work and I didn't know how
to explain that. It was my first
attempt. So, I didn't know how to
communicate that. But, um, that was one
of the attempts and it goes into great
detail on that attempt, but I ended up
going to the Utah compound. So, that was
good for me because there's mixture of
people there. There's XFLDS as well as
FLDS. So that's actually ultimately
where I did escape from. I have a few
experiences where I was like trying to
coordinate my escape and they ended up
sending me back to Texas for a short
time. And there is a picture that was
taken in Texas that has like all of his
wives, you know, has Warren Jeff's
picture behind him. I'm in that picture
because of one of those times that they
just transformed me back to Texas. You
know, I didn't really have a lot of say
in that. Now, I have testified against
Warren Jeffs in federal prison and been
told that my like it's been confirmed
that like my whole experience was
trafficking across state lines. I
escaped on May 23rd of 2012.
It wasn't actually in the building of
like Warren Jessel house like it was in
my brother's trailer at the park. I
tried to escape that morning
and took some main roads and was caught
on the roads that Fle called and told
them that I was running away. So, they
ended up bringing me back and then um
later that day I was in a room. They had
put like because I tried to escape, they
put like two screws in the window pane
so it would hit the the screws and then
the the doorork knob was turned around
so I couldn't unlock it on my side and
without the key which I didn't have a
key. So I um found some scissors in the
room and I unscrewed one side that was
really loose. The other side I just
pounded on it until it broke off. and
and the sister-in-law that was in the
house, she she came and looked in the
window outside and she said, "What are
you doing?" You know, she could hear me
pounding on it. She came in and took
everything I was using. I just found
other stuff. She actually called my
brother, but like he uh was in a
meeting, which I believe was God myself.
Um but the true God, you know, but like
when I did break off that screw, they
had told me to read earlier that day.
So, I thought if I just if I open any
drawers, they're going to know I left.
But if I just climb out the window, they
may think I laid down to read. They may
not know I have both screws undone. So,
I climbed out the window and I ran
through back roads this time through the
creek, got to a house that was
specifically XFLDS. And the family I ran
to by the end of the day drove me out of
town to an activist who picked me up and
brought me to her personal location
because they were just smaller
organizations at that time. They weren't
like they didn't have crisis houses.
They had like outreaches. So she took me
to her personal home in a neighboring
town. The next day the police officers
who were also FLDS at the time um I
couldn't even call 911 in Short Creek
cuz it would get the FLDS police force.
I ended up finding an organization that
had a family in Nashville that would
take me in and they drove me to Colorado
to make sure I wasn't intercepted at the
airport cuz that they were hunting for
me, you know, like my FLDS family was
hunting for me. I just felt like, you
know, I need more support than what I'm
getting cuz like they were always
concerned that I wasn't eating, you
know, my mental health was like kind of
out of hand cuz I wasn't in SAR mode. I
felt safe. Prior to going to Tennessee,
I called the domestic violence shelter
in Tennessee and asked them if they
would take me on my first case if I
needed it and they said they would. So,
I ended up like staying there for like 3
months and doing good on some days. Some
days I would do bad. It took me about 6
months to have constant clarity. They
transported me to another domestic
violence shelter that was
Christian-based and I stayed there also
for 3 months. I had my first Christmas
ever in my life in a domestic violence
shelter in Tennessee. Like it was it was
amazing. But like they they had a bunch
of donations come. I remember being so
overwhelmed that I just kept walking out
of the room and coming back in. It was
interesting. But like um I ended up
going a few places in Nashville. I ended
up in like a mental health more type
facility cuz they had a lot of resources
in that area.
It usually takes they say about 10 years
before you see significant change in the
community in the way people perceive
you. I've seen now I've been out 14
years so I've seen that shift at 10
years about my name was Lynette Warner
um before and I changed it to Briel
Decker Blanchard and changed my social
security number in America. When I got
out of the church, um it took me a while
to figure out like details banking. Um I
did go I learned that in Nashville there
was some bankers that came into the
shelter and gave us some education and I
opened up my first banking account based
on that. I remember when I met my
husband, I saw the ocean for the first
time in my life on our honeymoon in
Santa Monica, California. I you know
just stuff like that is so special to me
because like I didn't think I'd ever get
to like when I saw the Statue of Liberty
for the first time in my life. It was so
special to me because like you know I'm
a woman in America you know like that
finally gets to experience freedom you
know and that's what the Statue of
Liberty represents is freedom. My middle
name is um liberte which is French for
liberty. When the men leave they have
more skills. They they usually have like
they've been working for years and they
also get higher paying jobs, but the
women when they leave, they don't know
how to survive out here as well. It's
just come they might know how to sew,
you know, and they don't get paid very
much. It's harder to learn how to
thrive. I was changing my social my all
that, but they didn't change my SSI in
the same month. They qualified me for
SSI, but like when they changed my
social security number, they were still
going to change my SSI, but they hadn't
yet. So, I couldn't pay my rent. So, I
called my attorney in Utah and I was
like, "What do I do? I don't know how to
pay my rent." He's like, "I don't know
how to do that. They're still going to
do it, but I don't know how to speed it
up." So, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to tell you that there was this
exfelliious man who walked in my office
and told me that he was kicked out when
he was a boy. He was like a lost boy. He
grew up. He became a pilot, graduated
from pilot school, and walked in his
office and gave him some crisis tickets.
And he said, "If anybody's in crisis,
tell them to fly home because Short
Creek is changing from FLDS to XFLDS."
And he these crisis tickets were
airplane tickets that go on the back of
the plane if there's any seats. So I was
like, "That sounds crazy." But you know,
I have to go back to Utah after going
through witness protection. It was just
crazy. So I ended up in Salt Lake with
an exfest
house in Short Creek and went after it
for the recovery center. like it's a
mansion. It has like 45 rooms. And I was
awarded the house in 2016 on
Thanksgiving Day. I applied in February
of 2016. And then I went on a hunt. I
did free tours of the house and media
cuz it was a high-profile house. I
wanted like the dream which was to build
a recovery center. And I found like with
the help of like some Christians that
came through on free tours, um I was
able to locate a worldwide organization
called the Dream Center in Phoenix. and
they
agreed to, you know, like do a lease to
own, make sure they could get their
licensing in Hillell. That's the first
business to get licensing after War and
Jess left, you know, and now they've
been open for like since 2017, you know,
like, you know, it's been six years
more, I think. So, I had a a salary
position to do like media for the first
three years. Today I am a peer support
specialist, a case manager, also a um
residential aid at the Short Creek Dream
Center. The majority are like victims of
something, but like we do prioritize
people from the like FLDS or XFLDS,
but um and also other polygamy groups.
There's a lot of gaps in this area like
we need senior citizen nonprofit. The
elderly can't always get out right now
cuz ours has stairs. We don't have
elevators. Also, daycare in the town
that we have is a big gap because like
if we had a daycare, then we could um
more adequately help the single moms.
I do not think the church ended when
Warren just went to prison. He is the
prophet of the FLDS church until he
dies. So that's how their doctrine is.
God would kill the leader before he'd
allow him to lead the people astray.
He's in prison for life in 20 years for
a reason. Um, but he still is leading
the FLDS from prison. I think it'd be
worse if he hadn't have been arrested. I
believe him being alive in prison has
helped a lot more people wake up than
just starting over with a new leader
immediately with his execution. the FLDS
um is usually linked to Warren Jeffs,
but there are possibility that they
could call themselves FLDS without being
Warren Jeff's their prophet because it's
just a branch off the LDS church. So
they have doctrines that they highlight
in their over the pulpit even that are
dangerous for children especially like
underage brides. They have doctrines in
their in their faith about racism. The
Mormons, I mean like the LDS, Latter-day
Saints people have taken it out like
they after several years they had a
prophet that said now is the time to
accept everyone. So they have less
racism in the Latter-day Saints faith.
But in the polygamy groups, there's like
23 polygamy groups. I don't know of one
that has changed the original doctrine
to be accept race like any race into
their church. And it's really hard to to
to figure out a way to to incorporate a
new belief once cuz it would be like
denouncing their prophets of the past if
they say that doctrine was not true. So
they have to figure out a a creative way
to incorporate like modern day into
their faith. So it's really complicated
to to change the doctrine. So when they
put underage brides in the FLDS faith,
they can't take it out very easy. So if
they're following FLDS necessarily, it
doesn't mean they're following Warren
Jeffs cuz that's just a branch off of
the Latter Day Saints. But if they are
following Warren Jeffs, most likely they
have arranged marriages, also underage
brides marriages. So they're going to
need investigated. The main thing is
underage brides in FLBS. There are other
things like I know in like the AUB and
the Kingston group, it's been more about
like Jesus is our elder brother cuz in
the Mormon faith Jesus is our elder
brother instead of like an all powerful
being in the Joseph Smith teachings. But
in the FLDS they do have that but not
over the pulpit so much. So still a
problem. So there are criminal
activities you know like you know
because that could damage all the
children you know if you're marry too in
intermaring
um they can get like
handicapped more easily and then
underage brides is also like you know
trapping the children into a cycle where
they have children. you know, it's
illegal to do that, but like, you know,
they have children when they get old
enough to realize they're kind of
trapped in a cycle. They have to feed
their kids and also like escape somehow
with their kids, you know, like it's a
way bigger job when they have children
at 13, you know what I mean? So, um it's
definitely illegal. So there are reasons
why it's illegal too because we want to
protect instead of like
take away people's freedom based on um
what our country is made for you know
freedom you know what I mean freedom of
religion especially you know like we
have to watch those those those lines
why they're there and you know keep it
safe this country safe polygamy in
general in Utah is an infraction now
where everywhere else in America it's a
felony. I don't think it's going to end.
Like I think there's just going to be
more polygamy groups over time.
Hi, I'm a producer on How Crime Works.
If you enjoyed this video, then please
subscribe and comment below with more
ideas of topics you'd like us to cover
in this series.